VIVEK L ALEX

Certified Datascience Practitioner

J +91- **≥** vivekalexktr@gmail.com inlinkedin.com/in/viveklalex oviveklalex.github.io **M** Medium

∠ kaggle

SUMMARY

Engineer with proven experience in artificial intelligence application development and object oriented programming. Determined to add value to your team as a continuous learner. Excellent analytical problem solving and research aptitude using strategic methodology and requires minimal supervision. Expertise in areas of implementing and optimizing machine learning models, collecting and improving quality of data, and finding useful insights.

EXPERIENCE

 Omdena Remote

Junior Machine Learning Engineer Completed:

Oct. 2021 - Present.

o Using AI to improve road safety in Hyderabad, Telangana, (Scrapping, NLP modelling task, Making Computer vision model and Docker the Project)

Insightsearch

Remote

Author and Maintainer

Aug. 2021 - Present.

- o Insightsearch is a python package for analyzing customer reviews and texts.
- It can extract sentiments, aspect and opinions without the pain of complex workflow.
- o Insightsearch is built on on top of popular NLP frameworks include Spacy, TextBlob and NLTK.
- o Insightsearch includes rule based aspect extraction algorithms and sentiment extraction with inbuilt sentiment analyzers.

• Futurspot.in (discont.) [Link]

Remote *Jan.* 2021 – *Present*. Developer and Technical Content Creator

- o Created blogging web platform using HTML, CSS, JavaScript and Django.
- o Implemented text to speech model for the platform
- o Creating social media contents, articles and blogs on latest technological innovations around the world.
- o Optimizing content to search engine criteria

Algomox Pvt Ltd

AI developer

Banglore, India Feb. 2020 – Dec. 2020

- o Research and implementation of solutions for real world problems using Deep learning, machine learning, NLP, and computer vision
- o Created machine learning models for banking and financial services, E commerce, and health care & life sciences
- o Work with machine learning engineers, product managers and analysts to solve problems within business context
- o Research, Develop, Deploy and optimization of deep learning algorithms
- o Developed intent classification algorithm for chat bot Norra using LSTM architecture for automating L1 IT support

Wintech Technology Solutions

Electronics and Robotics Intern

Kerala, India

2017 - 2017

• PCB and circuit designing for different product categories

EDUCATION

Calicut, India National institute of electronics and information technology Advance Diploma In Artificial Intelligence 2019 - 2019Percentage: 94% Cochin college of engineering and technology Kerala, India

Bachelors of Technology in Mechatronics Engineering CGPA: 7.18

2015 - 2019

TECHNICAL SUMMARY

- Data Science: Data analysis, Machine learning, Natural language processing, Statistics, Probability, Linear Algebra, Time Series Computer vision, Data mining
- **Programming**: Python, SQL, JavaScript
- Frameworks: Tensor flow, Keras, Pytorch, ROS, Flask, Django
- Analytical Tools: Scikit-learn, PyCaret, NLTK, Pandas, Open CV, NumPy, Spacy, SciPy, Selenium, Scrapy, Beautiful soup
- Visualization Tools: Matplotlib, Plotly, Seaborn, Tableau
- Others: Git, Docker, MySQL, KiCAD, Arduino, Raspberry pi

COURSES

- Tableau training
- Deep Learning
- Data Science with Python
- Introduction to SQL
- Internet of things(Udemy)
- ROS basics, navigation(Udemy)
- Introduction to Data Analytics
- NLP and Text Mining Tutoria
- Basics of Web Scraping with Beautiful Soup
- Introduction to Neural Network

PROJECTS

• BOSTON RESTAURANT LOCATION CASE STUDY: [Project link]

- ➤ Choose an Ideal Site for Designing Restaurant Using Data Science
- > Data is collected and pre-processed into clean data suitable for a machine learning model
- > Used **K-means** and **Principle component analysis** to segment Boston based on location characters.
- **SUMMARY CREATOR**: [Project link]
 - ➤ Abstractive text summarizer for english news.
 - > Scrapped Data from News websites [Scrappers link]
 - > Applied **T5 transformer** for summarizing tasks and Achieved BLEU score of .00.
 - ➤ Used **Flask** to create the app and **Dockerized** the whole project.
- FACE RECOGNIZER WITH TRIPLET LOSS: [Project link]
 - > Studied the research paper **FaceNet** and Implemented a face recognizer.
 - > Created a base model using TensorFlow and Implemented custom loss function called Triplet Loss
- HEART ATTACK ANALYSIS AND PREDICTION: [Project link]
 - > EDA on the data to find insights. Implemented multiple models based on accuracy, and recall
 - > hyper-parameter tuning using Optuna, models used Decision Tree, LGBM, Logistic regression, Bagging Classifier and Gradient Boosting, finally used Voting Classifier (hard-voting)
- DEEP AND WIDE RECOMMENDATION SYSTEM: [Project link]
 - > Wide and **Deep recommendation system** using Tensorflow
 - > Implemented **Deep and wide** architecture
- CUSTOMER SEGMENTATION USING RFM: [Project link]
 - > Recommended marketing actions by segmenting customers on the basis of **RFM score** (Recency, Frequency, Monetary)
 - ➤ Used **k-Means** clustering and managerial perspective to make customer segments.